export const HISTORYA2018 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. The study of History promotes all the following except",
A: "tolerance.",
B: "patriotism.",
C: "employment.",
D: "racism.",
answer: "C. employment.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. A merit of archaeological finding is that it",
A: "cannot be destroyed by fire.",
B: "can be stored in a museum.",
C: "can last for a few days.",
D: "can be seen and touched.",
answer: "D. can be seen and touched.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. The best method used for the reconstruction of West African history is the use of",
A: "archaeological approach.",
B: "carbon-14 dating.",
C: "inter-disciplinary approach.",
D: "numismatics.",
answer: "C. inter-disciplinary approach.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. Sources of history have been divided into two main groups. These are:",
A: "past and present",
B: "accurate and incorrect",
C: "current and future",
D: "documentary and non-documentary",
answer: "D. documentary and non-documentary",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. The most important article of the trans-Saharan trade which strengthened the military system of most West African states was the",
A: "horse.",
B: "giraffe.",
C: "camel.",
D: "elephant.",
answer: "A. horse.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. The use of camel in the trans-Saharan trade brought all these advantages except",
A: "maintaining a regular pace of 25 to 30 km a day.",
B: "withstanding both daytime heat and night time cold.",
C: "travelling up to 10 days without drinking water.",
D: "the inability to carry weighty loads.",
answer: "D. the inability to carry weighty loads.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. The Tuareg contributed to the development of the trans-Saharan trade in the following ways except",
A: "cultivation of food crops for the caravans.",
B: "provision of drinking water.",
C: "robbing traders of their personal belongings.",
D: "serving as guides and interpreters.",
answer: "C. Becoming administrators in the Western Sudanese courts",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. One of the benefits derived from the trans-Saharan trade was the",
A: "breaking of the barrier caused by the Sahara desert.",
B: "increase in the number of West Africans that migrated to North Africa.",
C: "increase in the number of Europeans who settled in West Africa.",
D: "introduction of European food crops in West Africa.",
answer: "B. development of towns and cities.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. Which of the following developments was not an effect of the trans-Saharan trade on West Africa?",
A: "Islamic civilization was introduced",
B: "Introduction of new ideas.",
C: "West African states were known to the outside world",
D: "West African rulers were controlled by merchants",
answer: "B. dried dates.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. Educated Muslims held the following positions in the administration of many West African Kingdoms except",
A: "judges.",
B: "advisers.",
C: "scribes.",
D: "rulers.",
answer: "A. it accommodated the traditional cultures.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. The introduction of Islam into West Africa was initially done through",
A: "military invasion.",
B: "free distribution of the Holy Quran.",
C: "peaceful means.",
D: "free distribution of food.",
answer: "B. the spread of Islamic religion to West Africa.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. Which of the following was not an effect of the spread of Islam in West Africa?",
A: "Introduction of Arabic architecture",
B: "A new form of education and literacy in Arabic was introduced",
C: "Arabic law and language became important in commerce",
D: "West African customs and cultures were cancelled",
answer: "D. rulers.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. Islam appealed to many West African societies mainly because",
A: "it promised forgiveness of all sins.",
B: "the Koran was easy to read.",
C: "it permitted some customary practices.",
D: "it encouraged alms-giving.",
answer: "B. the spread of Islamic religion.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. The spread of Islam in West Africa was mainly the work of",
A: "Fulani.",
B: "Mandingo.",
C: "Creole.",
D: "Kanuri.",
answer: "C. Trade",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. The coastal traders in some West African states resisted European penetration into the interior because the Europeans",
A: "would defy their local deities.",
B: "wanted to champion local activities.",
C: "would displace them as middlemen.",
D: "wanted to introduce western education.",
answer: "A. Rise and development of towns",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. European contact with West Africans led to",
A: "enslavement of West African chiefs.",
B: "safe-keeping of many European merchants.",
C: "inter-ethnic wars among West Africans.",
D: "European knowledge of many places in West Africa.",
answer: "D. trade in gold and ivory.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. Which of the following was not an objective of the Europeans in West Africa? The desire to",
A: "introduce Christianity.",
B: "establish colonies.",
C: "spread European culture.",
D: "industrialize the area.",
answer: "A. decline of trans-Saharan trade.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. The main problem which initially hindered European contact with the indigenous people of West Africa was",
A: "language barrier.",
B: "shortage of funds.",
C: "marriage alliances.",
D: "shortage of personnel.",
answer: "C. Portuguese.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. West Africans mainly reacted to European penetration because they",
A: "suspected they would take over their lands.",
B: "regarded them as object of admiration.",
C: "did not bring gifts for them from Europe.",
D: "did not want to participate in international trade.",
answer: "B. find a sea route to India and the Far East.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. The common article of trade which European traders sought on the West African coast in the 18th century was",
A: "spices.",
B: "ivory.",
C: "slaves.",
D: "salt.",
answer: "B. African and European traders benefitted from it.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. The first European nation to participate in the trans-Atlantic slave trade was",
A: "Portugal.",
B: "Italy.",
C: "Britain.",
D: "France.",
answer: "A. Portugal.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. Which of the following was not an effect of the trans-Atlantic slave trade in West Africa?",
A: "Depopulation of communities",
B: "Promotion of African heritage",
C: "Retardation of indigenous industries",
D: "Decline in agriculture",
answer: "B. Promotion of African heritage",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. The most significant action which hastened the suppression of slavery and slave trade in West Africa was the",
A: "training of the populace against the trade.",
B: "introduction of traditional education.",
C: "moral and humanitarian appeal against the trade.",
D: "adequate support of African chiefs for the abolition.",
answer: "C. moral and humanitarian appeal against the trade.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. Which European nation passed an Act in parliament in 1807 making the selling and buying of sla ves illegal?",
A: "Denmark",
B: "Netherlands",
C: "United States",
D: "Britain",
answer: "D. Britain",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. The primary objective of putting West African languages into writing by Christian missions was to",
A: "educate the illiterate Africans.",
B: "raise funds for their activities.",
C: "spread Western culture.",
D: "promote the spread of Christianity.",
answer: "D. promote the spread of Christianity.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. The Christian missions are best remembered in West Africa in the 19th century for the introduction of",
A: "guns and gunpowder.",
B: "new and beautiful architecture.",
C: "slavery and slave trade.",
D: "strong alcoholic drinks.",
answer: "B. introduction of Western education.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. The main reason for the coming of Christian missionaries to West Africa was to",
A: "convey Christian message to West Africans.",
B: "protect European slave traders.",
C: "introduce missionary work only in Sierra Leone.",
D: "know about West Africa.",
answer: "A. convey Christian message to West Africans.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. The Christian missionariesâ€™ compassion for the less privileged led to their",
A: "provision of humanitarian services.",
B: "destruction of Africa culture.",
C: "support for traditional religion.",
D: "encouragement of traditional medicine.",
answer: "A. provision of humanitarian services.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. The people of West Africa were displeased with the Christian missions because they",
A: "promoted technical education.",
B: "disrespected their culture.",
C: "introduced new European crops.",
D: "removed many traditional chiefs from power.",
answer: "B. disrespected their culture.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. The Scramble for and Partition of West Africa by the European powers was mainly fuelled by their desire to",
A: "enlighten the West Africans.",
B: "extend their political control",
C: "maintain trade monopoly.",
D: "make friends with West Africans.",
answer: "B. extend their political control",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. The European leader who summoned the Berlin Conference was",
A: "King Leopold II.",
B: "Otto von Bismarck.",
C: "Napoleon Bonaparte.",
D: "Jules Ferry.",
answer: "B. Otto von Bismarck.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. The Europeans had great advantage over the West Africans at the Berlin Conference because",
A: "West African countries lacked funds to attend the meetings.",
B: "the deliberations did not concern the West Africans.",
C: "economic sanction was placed on the West Africans.",
D: "there were no West African representatives at the conference.",
answer: "D. there were no West African representatives at the conference.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. The Industrial Revolution influenced the Scramble for and Partition of West Africa because it",
A: "created the need for the investment of European surplus capital.",
B: "delayed the process of sovereignty in West African countries.",
C: "reached the highest degree for the appointment of consuls in West Africa.",
D: "absorbed European domestic problems that preceded colonial activity.",
answer: "A. created the need for the investment of European surplus capital.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. West African states were effectively occupied by European nations after the partition due to",
A: "the approval of the European powers.",
B: "their possession of superior weaponry.",
C: "the support given by the Americans.",
D: "their determination to spread Western education.",
answer: "B. their possession of superior weaponry.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. Which of the following economic factors mainly influenced the Scramble for and Partition of West Africa?",
A: "Promotion of African traditional industries",
B: "The quest for food crops to feed the captured slaves",
C: "The need for raw materials and markets for European goods",
D: "Introduction and enforcement of legitimate trade",
answer: "C. The need for raw materials and markets for European goods",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. The headquarters of the French government in West Africa was located in",
A: "Abidjan.",
B: "Lome.",
C: "Dakar.",
D: "Bamako.",
answer: "C. Dakar.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. The British colonial rule in West Africa generally resulted in the",
A: "exploitation of West African mineral resources.",
B: "removal of West African chiefs from power.",
C: "abolition of West African traditional cultures.",
D: "abolition of the trans-Atlantic slave trade.",
answer: "A. exploitation of West African mineral resources.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. In administering her colonies in West Africa, the British relied heavily on the",
A: "educated Africans.",
B: "African merchants.",
C: "traditional rulers.",
D: "Christian missionaries.",
answer: "C. traditional rulers.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. The policy of Assimilation was based on the idea of",
A: "French superiority.",
B: "African inferiority.",
C: "Western superiority.",
D: "human equality.",
answer: "C. Western superiority.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. One of the factors that threatened colonial rule in West Africa after World War II was the",
A: "increase in population.",
B: "increase in socio-political awareness.",
C: "experienced in technological advancement.",
D: "massive development in agriculture.",
answer: "B. increase in socio-political awareness.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. The colonial African boundaries created by the Europeans led to",
A: "rapid development of African states.",
B: "the promotion of African unity.",
C: "the outbreak of boundary conflicts.",
D: "the development of local industries.",
answer: "C. the outbreak of boundary conflicts.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. The military intervened in West Africa politics mainly to",
A: "punish political offenders.",
B: "establish more industries.",
C: "correct economic mismanagement.",
D: "prove that might is right.",
answer: "C. correct economic mismanagement.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. A disadvantage of ethnic politics is the quest by members of the ruling group to",
A: "cause trouble for the other ethnic groups.",
B: "be flown abroad on vacations.",
C: "be given preferential treatment.",
D: "topple the government in power.",
answer: "C. be given preferential treatment.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. Neo-colonialism in West Africa is seen as â€˜government by remote controlâ€™ because their governments",
A: "are engineered by remote control.",
B: "often use remote control.",
C: "could not direct their own affairs.",
D: "are well managed.",
answer: "C. its political policies are dictated by some powerful forces from outside.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. A major achievement of the military in West African politics is",
A: "taking quick and bold decisions.",
B: "teaching the civilians the art of governance.",
C: "eradication of corruption in public services.",
D: "preventing corrupt politicians from participating in politics.",
answer: "A. Taking quick and bold decisions.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. One major effect of boundary disputes on African unity was the",
A: "non-participation of some African countries in the meetings of O.A.U.",
B: "prevention of peaceful atmosphere that could promote unity.",
C: "free movement of goods and people across different international borders.",
D: "inability of West African states to establish trade relations with one another.",
answer: "B. prevention of peaceful atmosphere that could promote unity.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. The veto power at the United Nations is exercised by",
A: "all members of the United Nations.",
B: "the non-permanent members of the Security Council.",
C: "only the five permanent members of the Security Council.",
D: "only fifty members of the General Assembly.",
answer: "C. only the five permanent members of the Security Council.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. Free movement of people, goods and services is one main aim of the",
A: "Commonwealth.",
B: "Non-Aligned Movement.",
C: "African Union.",
D: "Economic Community of West African States.",
answer: "D. Economic Community of West African States.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. All the following options were principal aims of the Organization of African Unity (O.A.U.) except",
A: "bringing unity among member states.",
B: "driving all Europeans out of Africa.",
C: "improving the lives of all Africans.",
D: "achieving independence for all its members.",
answer: "B. driving all Europeans out of Africa.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. The United Nations Organization (U.N.O.) is the main body through which nations of the world",
A: "make trade agreements.",
B: "market their countries.",
C: "co-operate among themselves.",
D: "promote sporting activities.",
answer: "C. co-operate among themselves.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},


]